<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Humble proposals to the Parliament now assembled whereby the profession of the civil law may be used in certain cases to the great ease and benefit of the people : without looking back to Episcopacy or any thing that is abolished, or making any use of the Pope's law commonly called The Canon law or taking away any thing from the Common law, and in a perfect compliance with this present government.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45083</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3600</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28932</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10784588</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10784588</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45845</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45083)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45845)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1387:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Humble proposals to the Parliament now assembled whereby the profession of the civil law may be used in certain cases to the great ease and benefit of the people : without looking back to Episcopacy or any thing that is abolished, or making any use of the Pope's law commonly called The Canon law or taking away any thing from the Common law, and in a perfect compliance with this present government.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E.C. for R. Royston,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament.</term>
               <term>Civil law --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45845:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 61 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:45845:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 61 -->
            <p>HUMBLE PROPOSALS TO THE PARLIAMENT Now Aſſembled.</p>
            <p>Whereby the Profeſſion of the <hi>CIVIL LAW</hi> may be uſed in certain Caſes, to the great eaſe and benefit of the People, without looking back to <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> or any thing that is aboliſhed, or making any uſe of the <hi>Popes Law,</hi> commonly called the <hi>The Canon Law,</hi> or taking away any thing from the <hi>Common Law,</hi> and in a perfect com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with this preſent Government.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. C.</hi> for <hi>R. Royſton</hi> at the Angel in <hi>Ivie-lane,</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:45845:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 62 -->
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:45845:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 62 -->
            <head>HUMBLE PROPOSALS TO THE PARLIAMENT Now Aſſembled.</head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> FIrſt and principally, they do declare, That they hove ſo far razed out of their thoughts any power, whether <hi>Civil</hi> or <hi>Ecleſiaſtical,</hi> that has been aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and do ſo little intend the uſe of the <hi>Canon Law,</hi> and leaſt of all to abridge the <hi>Common Law</hi> in any thing, that they are very willing, that in any <hi>Act</hi> that ſhall be made for the exerciſe of their Profeſſion, ſome ſuch clauſes may be inſerted, whereby the people of this Nation may be ſatisfied in theſe particulars;</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That it is done for the continuance of the ſtudy of the <hi>Civil Law</hi> only, that is ſo uſeful for determining mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters done upon the Sea, correſpondence with forein Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and publick Tranſactions both of Peace and War.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:45845:3"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 63 -->
2. That all their proceedings ſhall go in the name and ſtyle of the preſent Government, and ſtamp'd with ſuch inſcription and ſeal, as ſhall be allowed.</item>
               <item>3. That it ſhall not be lawful for any, either <hi>Judge</hi> or <hi>Advocate</hi> of that Profeſſion, to vouch or cite in Court for authority any part of the <hi>Canon Law,</hi> nor any <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Law</hi> heretofore of uſe in this Nation, but ſhall vouch the Civil Law only.</item>
               <item>4. That if in the caſes permitted them to exerciſe their Profeſſion in, there be any Law of the Nation expreſſe in the caſe, no <hi>Judge</hi> or <hi>Advocate</hi> ſhall preſume to cite the <hi>Civil Law</hi> to the contrary, but ſhall leave it to be decided by the eſtabliſhed Law of the Nation.</item>
               <item>5. That thereby nothing is intended to be granted to the <hi>Civilians,</hi> that by any Act of Parliament, or the ancient uſages of this Nation has belonged to the coniſance of the <hi>Common Law.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Secondly, They do ſo perfectly deſire to conform to the deſires of the ſeveral Countreys of this Common-wealth, to have juſtice adminiſtred within the Countrey without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to <hi>London,</hi> that as to the doing of juſtice in the caſes hereunder mentioned, they ſhall be ready to ſerve them in ſuch places of the Countrey as the Parliament ſhall appoint, as formerly they did, though under another capacity and notion then heretofore.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> Thirdly, They do not aime to graſp or reach at any thing which has not alwaies belonged unto them heretofore, or which any other <hi>Court</hi> or <hi>Law</hi> can challenge; but do juſtly hope, that what they Petition for, ſhall be continued in them, becauſe they have a certain rule for thoſe caſes in the <hi>Civil Law,</hi> and the <hi>Common Law</hi> has none.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> Fourthly, The ſeveral matters that they deſire to exerciſe their profeſſion in, are none of them <hi>Papal</hi> or <hi>Epiſcopal,</hi> but ſuch as will commonly happen amongſt the people under this preſent Government, and which all well ordered States, for the quiet and ſatisfaction of the people, do provide for.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:45845:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 63 -->
Theſe things being premiſed, the matters whereof they deſire to have the coniſance and trial in the ſeveral Countreys, are theſe enſuing;</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Probats</hi> of <hi>Wills,</hi> as to perſonal Eſtate only.</p>
            <p>This has alwaies undeniably belonged unto the Courts of the <hi>Civil Law</hi> only.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Granting of <hi>Adminiſtrations,</hi> where perſons dye <hi>inteſtate,</hi> and without any <hi>Will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. To call for <hi>Inventaries</hi> and <hi>Accounts</hi> upon them.</p>
            <p>Of theſe two there has never been any queſtion neither.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Diſtribution of <hi>Portions</hi> out of the <hi>Goods</hi> and <hi>Perſonal Eſtate</hi> of ſuch as ſhall dye without any <hi>Will</hi> made, amongſt Wife, Children, or Kindred.</p>
            <p>Of this there hath been ſome queſtion made, whether the Courts of the <hi>Civil Law</hi> might do it or no; and the <hi>Courts</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> have ſometimes ſent Prohibitions to ſtop them from proceeding to execute any ſuch power. But yet they never undertook to diſtribute Portions themſelves, nor have, or pretend to have any Rules for it. And in caſes where <hi>Prohibitions</hi> have not come (as not one in a hundred Caſes has) diſtributions have been conſtantly for many Ages practiſed by the Courts of the <hi>Civil Law.</hi> That therefore there is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity to ſettle them finally ſomewhere, and rather in the <hi>Civil Law</hi> then any were elſe: there be theſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons;</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Becauſe the <hi>Common Law</hi> for want of Rule and practiſe, cannot order them, nor ever did.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:45845:4"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 64 -->
2. Becauſe the <hi>Civil Law</hi> has certain Rules for them in every Caſe, the Caſes whereof are very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and ſome very difficult.</item>
               <item>3. Becauſe elſe the Adminiſtrator, that gets the Adminiſtration, after debts paid, will keep all the reſt to himſelfe, though there be never ſo many as near of Kin as he; and ſo it may happen, that the eldeſt ſon that has all the Land, by getting <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration,</hi> may have all the Goods too, and the reſt of the children have nothing out of their Fathers Eſtate to keep them; for if a <hi>Prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> come, the younger children are without any remedy.</item>
               <item>4. Becauſe this matter of <hi>Diſtributions</hi> is but an appendant or acceſſory to <hi>Adminiſtrations,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is requiſite, that both ſhould be decided by one and the ſame <hi>Judicatory.</hi> And if practiſe and knowledge may make out to any a Title to them; the <hi>Civilians</hi> have moſt to ſay for themſelves, being alwaies practiſed, and having moſt skill in them both.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="5">5. Cauſes of <hi>Mariage, Divorce,</hi> and <hi>Alimony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the firſt there will be uſe, when two perſons have by <hi>formal promiſe</hi> each to other contracted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in mariage, ſo that nothing is wanting to make them Man and Wife, but the ceremony of marying, and yet the one denies ſuch promiſe, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſes to perform it, or happily maries another man or woman.</p>
            <p>This may be ſo ſetled, as not to intrench or derogate from the late <hi>Act of Mariages,</hi> if that be thought fit to continue of force ſtill; for the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity of Marying may ſtill be the ſame, as that Act appointeth, This new intended proviſion is but to ſupply thoſe Caſes, which that Act has
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45845:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 64 -->declared nothing in. Beſides, the ſubjects hereby ſhall have but a double remedy, leaving them to go to the <hi>Juſtices</hi> or <hi>Seſſions,</hi> or to this <hi>new Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatory;</hi> But where the complaint is firſt entied, it ſhall be a Bar to hinder the other from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding.</p>
            <p>Of the ſecond, namely, <hi>Divorces,</hi> there is uſe, when two perſons marry one another, that for near <hi>kindred</hi> or <hi>alliance,</hi> or ſome other <hi>Legal impediment,</hi> are not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to intermary; or when one maried perſon is quite forſaken by the other, and is not heard of in many years, and is reported to be dead; or when ſuch irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concilable enmity is hapned between them, that they may be better ſevered as to cohabitation, then permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to live together.</p>
            <p>That of <hi>Alimony</hi> is uſeful, when the Husband will live aſunder from his Wife, and yet will allow her no maintenance, or uſes her with more cruelty then can be endured. In which caſe the duty of cohabita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may be taken off, and the Husband may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned to allow the Wife Alimony and maintenance to ſuch proportion as his Eſtate can bear.</p>
            <p>Of theſe ſeverall Caſes the <hi>Civil Law</hi> has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies had the Coniſance, the <hi>Common Law</hi> never did pretend to any of them. The <hi>Chancery</hi> has by ſpecial orders of late ordered <hi>Alimony,</hi> but that was becauſe the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Courts</hi> were abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, and was intended only to ſerve for a preſent ſupply of juſtice, till a perfect ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment could be made, which now wee hope for.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:45845:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 65 -->
6. Cauſes of <hi>Legacies</hi> given by laſt Wills and Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, of Money, Goods, Chattels or other perſonall Eſtate; not of Lands, or any Freehold, which is recoverable only at <hi>Common Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since the fall of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction,</hi> theſe Cauſes have been <hi>pro tempore</hi> put into ſeverall hands to judge them, but intended for a preſent ſupply of juſtice only, and not to remain any longer there, then till a more perfect ſettlement could be made by Parliament.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Cauſes of <hi>Tithes,</hi> for ſo long time as that kinde of maintenance ſhall be kept up, excepting the Tithe of <hi>Corn</hi> and <hi>Hay,</hi> which is recoverable at <hi>Common Law</hi> by Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dammages.</p>
            <p>For the recovery, hereof ſince the taking away of the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Power,</hi> to prevent a failer of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, ſeveral Orders have been made and directions given to order them by other hands, but intended to endure no longer. then till a perfect ſettlement ſhould be made.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Repairs of <hi>Churches,</hi> and the payment of Rates to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, together with the keeping up of <hi>Parſonage</hi> and <hi>Vicatidge</hi> houſes; which were conſtantly ordered by the Courts of the <hi>Civil Law,</hi> and never otherwiſe: But only of late ſome orders were made in them, as in other Caſes above mentioned, for ſupply of juſtice for the preſent, to prevent imminent and daily miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:45845:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 65 -->
Theſe are the few Caſes that the <hi>Civilians</hi> are Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for, to exerciſe their Profeſſion in, throughout the ſeveral Countreys of this Common-wealth: In order to which, they pray,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That any Act or Bill, that ſhall be brought into the Parliament for the ſetling of theſe Caſes or any of them in any Judicatory in the Countrey, may have a Clauſe or a Proviſo in it; <hi>That the ſaid Caſes ſhall be tryed and judged by Civilians, and by the Rules of the Civil Law, as formerly they have been.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. That ſuch a <hi>Coercive Power</hi> may be granted to the <hi>Judges</hi> thereof, as may be ſufficient to make men appear to anſwer in the ſaid ſeveral and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Caſes, and to do and perform what ſhall be adjudg'd therein, that their keeping of Courts may not be in vain.</item>
               <item>3. That if any ſhall finde themſelves aggrieved by any <hi>final</hi> and <hi>diffinitive judgement,</hi> that ſhall be given upon the whole matter, and would run the hazard of a ſecond Trial, they may have liberty to appeal to the <hi>Lord Protector</hi> in the High Court of <hi>Chancery,</hi> and the Cauſe to be tryed by a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Delegates</hi> in ſuch manner, as alwaies former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly has been.</item>
            </list>
            <p>This may ſeem burthenſome, that all Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals ſhould be to <hi>London.</hi> But the difficulty and charge thereof will be ſuch a check to contentious ſpirits, that but upon weighty and juſt grounds, and in matters of moment, men will not be ſo eaſily tempted to appeal as they will when the charge is light, and the trouble not ſo great.</p>
            <p>Which Caſes except they be 'ſetled upon the Profeſſors of the <hi>Civil Law,</hi> thereby to employ
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45845:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 66 -->themſelves in, and to keep that learning on foot ſtill, ſo uſeful for all <hi>Maritime</hi> affairs, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Negotiations with <hi>forein States,</hi> that learning will be irrecoverably loſt for ever; and one whole calling, that the youth of this Nation was hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bred in and advanced by, will be quite taken away; for other means of preſerving it will not be found in a practicall way, which only can make it uſeful to this <hi>Common-wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:45845:6"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 66 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
